<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="EventAPI">
	<title>Event API</title>
	<indexterm><primary>Event API</primary></indexterm>
	<para>
		During execution of a test run, cfix generates a stream of events. This stream of events 
		includes information about failed assertions, log messages, and status information indicating
		when execution of a test case begins and ends.
	</para>
	<para>
		All this event information is delivered to an <emphasis>event sink</emphasis>. The default
		event sink used by cfix prints output to the console and is implemented in cfixcons.dll.
	</para>
	<para>
		Using the Event API, developers can implement custom event sinks that replace the default
		console event sink. A custom event sink could, for example, gather events and write them 
		to a log file in a specific format.
	</para>
	<para>
		Event sinks are implemented in <emphasis>Event DLLs</emphasis>. This design allows event 
		sinks to be generic and usable in combination with any kind of test module.
	</para>
	<para>
		Event DLLs have to provide a single exported routine named 
		<link linkend="CreateEventSink">CreateEventSink</link> -- this routine
		serves as a factory routine for event sinks. The cfix runtime will call this routine
		once before starting a test run and will use the returned event sink to deliver all 
		events to.
	</para>

	<section id="CustomEventSink">
		<title>Creating Custom Event Sinks</title>
		
		<simplesect>
		<para>
			Creating a custom event sink comprises two steps: First, you have to implement the interface defined
			by CFIX_EVENT_SINK. Second, you have to wrap your implementation in a separate DLL, the <emphasis>Event DLL </emphasis>
			and provide a specific export, <link linkend='CreateEventSink'>CreateEventSink</link>. Please refer to the 
			following subsections for details.
		</para>
		</simplesect>
		
	
		<section id="CreateEventSink">
			<title>CreateEventSink</title>
			<indexterm><primary>CreateEventSink</primary></indexterm>
			
			
			<simplesect>
				<title>Synopsis</title>
				<para>
				Event DLLs have to provide a single export named <emphasis>CreateEventSink</emphasis>.
				This routine serves as a factory routine for event sinks. The cfix runtime will call this routine
				once before starting a test run and will use the returned event sink to deliver all events to.
				</para>
			</simplesect>
			
			<simplesect>
				<title>Declaration</title>
				<programlisting>
CFIXAPI HRESULT CFIXCALLTYPE CreateEventSink(
	__in ULONG Version,
	__in ULONG Flags,
	__in_opt PCWSTR Options,
	__reserved ULONG Reserved,
	__out PCFIX_EVENT_SINK *Sink 
	);
				</programlisting>
			</simplesect>
			
			<simplesect>
				<title>Parameters</title>
				<para>
				[in] <emphasis>Version</emphasis>: Event API Version the event sink is expected to support. In order
				to ensure binary compatibility with future framework versions, implementors should compare the value
				passed in this paramerer with CFIX_EVENT_SINK_VERSION and return CFIX_E_UNSUPPORTED_EVENT_SINK_VERSION 
				in case of a mismatch.
				</para>
				<para>
				[in] <emphasis>Flags</emphasis>: May contain the flag CFIX_EVENT_SINK_FLAG_SHOW_STACKTRACE_SOURCE_INFORMATION,
				indicating that stack traces should include source and line information. Implementors are free to
				ignore this flag.
				</para>
				<para>
				[in] <emphasis>Options</emphasis>: Options string, may be used to allow users to pass additional information
				(e.g. a file path) to the DLL. The options string is not interpreted by the cfix runtim and may use any format.
				</para>
				<para>
				[in] <emphasis>Reserved</emphasis>: Reserved, always 0.
				</para>
				<para>
				[out] <emphasis>Sink</emphasis>: Resulting Event sink.
				</para>
			</simplesect>
			
			
			&TestApiEventDllRequirements17;
		</section>
		
		<section id="CFIX_EVENT_SINK">
			<title>CFIX_EVENT_SINK</title>
			<indexterm><primary>CFIX_EVENT_SINK</primary></indexterm>
			
			
			<simplesect>
				<title>Synopsis</title>
				<para>
				The CFIX_EVENT_SINK defines the interface of an event sink. The structure is defined
				in cfixevnt.h -- please refer to this header file for details on the structure.
				</para>
			</simplesect>
			
			&TestApiEventDllRequirements17;
		</section>
	</section>
</section>